Guide to the Wayne P. Ellis Collection of Kodakiana, 1886-1989 and undated
Wayne P. Ellis Collection of Kodakiana 1886-1989 and undated
Ellis, Wayne P.
8.0 Linear Feet 6620 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Wayne P. Ellis Collection of Kodakiana was acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1993. The processing of this collection was supported in part by gifts from the John and Kelly Hartman Foundation.
Biographical Note
1915 Born in Des Moines, Iowa
1937 B.S. in chemistry from the University of Maryland
1937 Became a member of the American Society for Testing and Materials. Also eventually became a member of the American Chemical Society, the American Society of Heating, Refrigerating and Air-Conditioning Engineers, and a Fellow of the American Institute of Chemists.
1939-1989 Worked for H. B. Fuller Company
1940-1990 Began collecting Kodakiana and related materials because of a "personal interest in business history and American entrepreneurs."
1974-1977 Served as Member of Board of Directors, American Society for Testing and Materials (ASTM)
1977-1979 Vice-President, ASTM
1989 Retired and became consultant on stands for materials such as thermal insulation, packaging, adhesives, building sealants and other materials.
1993 25 Sept. Died in Sellersville, Pa.
Wayne P. Ellis was a professional chemist who spent 45 years in industrial research, product development, and marketing of coatings, adhesives, and sealants. He was widely known as an expert in standards and was a leader in the American Society for Testing and Materials. He won awards in the field, published many articles and coauthored a book. Mr. Ellis also was an extraordinary collector in several areas, including Eastman Kodak Company advertising-related materials. He was well known to photographic history enthusiasts and dealers in photographic and advertising ephemera.
Collection Overview
The Wayne P. Ellis Collection of Kodakiana spans the dates 1886 to 1989, and was created by Mr. Ellis over the period of nearly four decades. Whereas many photographic collectors concentrate on cameras and photographs, Ellis emphasized advertising and marketing material. As a consequence, the collection is especially rich in print advertisements for Eastman Kodak products that were published in general interest periodicals beginning in the late 19th century. More unusual items are the product catalogs, how-to manuals for both amateur and professional photographers, serial publications for salesmen and photographers, and a variety of marketing and promotional items. There are several scrapbooks of advertising materials with considerable marginalia. The collection also includes training manuals and other publications for Kodak employees. In addition, many items in the collection deal with various aspects of the corporate history of Eastman Kodak from its earliest years up to the mid-20th century.
The collection contains little or no correspondence. There are scattered groups of photographs throughout the collection, though they are few in number. Many are formal and casual black and white photographs of Kodak staff members. Others were used for promotional or sales activities.
Processing Note
Some of Mr. Ellis's material was in excellent order; other items were in greater disarray. The collection has been arranged, as far as practical, according to the type of material. The series names given to each category are as clear and descriptive as possible.
No items were removed from the collection except for some duplicates. Decisions were made early in the processing of this collection, however, to separate several titles for individual cataloging. Notable among these is the entire run of the early periodical Kodakery (v. 1-19, 1913-1932) as well as many issues of the variably titled Photographic Review and Photographic Digest, and several others. All of these titles are part of the Rare Book, Manuscript and Special Collections Library and may be located using that library's online catalog by searching "Wayne P. Ellis" as a keyword. The separation of items may cause some small inconvenience to users of the collection, but it has been deemed impractical to reverse the situation after the fact.
Mr. Ellis also contributed over 160 books on various aspects of advertising to the Duke University Libraries; the titles have been cataloged in the usual fashion as individual books, and are identified in the library catalog as being part of the Wayne P. Ellis collection.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Ellis, Wayne P.
Marketing
Advertising
Display of merchandise
Sales promotion
Publicity
Eastman Kodak Company -- History.
Advertising -- Photographic apparatus -- History
Photographic industry -- United States -- History
Eastman, George, 1854-1932
Professional photographers.
Black and white photographs
Advertisements
Scrapbooks
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & marketing History
Contents of Collection
- Advertisements Series, 1886-1977 and undated
  Chiefly single-sheet loose advertisements related to photographic products. Color and monochromatic illustrations. Organized chronologically within boxes or folders. Several collections of advertisements are housed in scrapbooks. NOTE: Serials titles given in boxes 11-14 represent full issues of these titles; issues contain at least one Kodak advertisement (many are on back covers).
  - Contents of Box: (Box 1)
    - [circa 1890]-[circa 1909] and undated, (12 folders)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 2)
    - 1905-1909, (8 folders)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 3)
    - 1910-[circa 1920], (9 folders)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 4)
    - 1914-1916, (8 folders)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 5)
    - 1917-1920, (9 folders)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 6)
    - 1920-1923, (9 folders)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 7)
    - 1923-1929, (11 folders)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 8)
    - 1930-1940, (12 folders)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 9)
    - 1940-1952, (14 folders)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 10)
    - 1953-1977; international materials [197-], (12 folders)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 11)
    - Ladies Home Journal, June 1905, (7 folders)
    - Youth's Companion, July 1900-Nov. 1913
  - Contents of Box: (Box 12)
    - Youth's Companion, 1914 June 19-1926 August 5, (5 folders)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 13)
    - Outlook, 1898 June 4
    - Popular Photography, Sept. 1937, Aug. 1948
    - Life, 1911 June 15
    - Saturday Evening Post, 1942 Aug. 2
    - U.S. Camera, Apr. 1947
    - Illustrated London News, 1926 Oct. 16
    - Country Life In America, 1902-1903
  - Contents of Box: (Box 14)
    - Harper's, Dec. 1888, June 1905
    - National Geographic, Mar. 1908
    - Outing, May 1905, June 1906, May 1907
    - F. Leslie's Popular Monthly, July 1902
  - Contents of Box: (Box 15)
    - Advertisement Scrapbook, 1913-1914 and undated
      The two scrapbooks in boxes 15 and 16 contain many corporate ads for the Eastman Kodak Company, with considerable marginalia that detail aspects of publication. Includes many slight variants (near duplicates) of ads, order lists for ad publishing, clipped articles, typed speech on The Romance of Photography, personally created ads, and magazine article about George Eastman.
  - Contents of Box: (Box 16)
    - Advertisement Scrapbook, 1914-1915 and undated
  - Contents of Box: (Box 17)
    - Advertisements in National Geographic
      - Still cameras, 1916-1973
      - Movie cameras, 1920-1967 and undated
      - "We do the rest"
        - 1900-1943
        - 1940-1973
  - Contents of Box: (Box 18)
    - Photography advertisements, Kodak and other, 1889-1911
    - Kodak camera ads by camera type, 1892-1959
    - Kodak lenses and filters, [1901?]-[1954?]
    - Graflex-Graphic, [1908?]-[1946?]
    - Hawk-eye cameras, [1892?]-[1934?]
    - Premo cameras and film, [1893?]-[1922?]
    - Kodak developing machines, [1902?]-[1912?]
    - Kodak film and paper, [1892?]-[1968?]
    - Kodak advertisements from Punch (London), [ca. 1920]-1931
    - Kodak Bulletin, [1939?]-[1945?]
  - Contents of Box: (Box 94)
    - Scrapbook #1 (advertisements) 1886-1901
  - Contents of Box: (Box 95)
    - Scrapbook #2 (advertisements) 1907-1924
- Eastman Kodak Company History Series, 1897-1986 and undated
  Reports, pamphlets, employee handbooks, and various other printed materials related to Kodak's corporate history. Includes annual reports and directors' reports, and several biographical works about George Eastman. Contents of title folders arranged chronologically.
  - Contents of Box: (Box 19)
    - Annual reports: Eastman Kodak Company, 1927-1946, (20 items)
    - Directors' Annual Report: Eastman Kodak Company
      - 1902-1914
      - 1906-1910
      - 1913-1916
      - 1918-1925, (19 items)
    - Kodak Works, 1897
  - Contents of Box: (Box 20)
    - The Home of Kodak, 1928-1934, (6 items)
    - George Eastman, 1930
    - George Eastman: A Brief Biography, 1953, (3 items)
    - George Eastman and the Research Bureau, 1954
    - Aristotle to Eastman, [1945?]
    - The Kodak Museum, 1947
  - Contents of Box: (Box 21)
    - Hawk-Eye..Kodak's Optical Works, 1951
    - Booklets about the George Eastman House, 1954, 1979, (2 items)
    - Kodak Milestones, 1967-1977, (5 items)
    - Welcome to Kodak Park, 1976
    - How Your Pictures are Processed at Kodak, 1975-1976 and undated, (3 items)
    - A Brief History: Eastman Kodak Company, 1978, 1957, [ca. 1966], (3 items)
    - How Kodak Got Its Name, 1980
    - Click! A Story About George Eastman, 1986
    - C. E. Kenneth Mees: Pioneer of Industrial Research, undated
    - Kodak Park: Its Products and People, 1949-1959, (4 items)
    - Story of the Kodak Camera, 1951
  - Contents of Box: (Box 22)
    - Various employee handbooks, 1919, 1925, 1935, 1938, 1942, 1947, 1985, undated, (12 items)
    - Honorary Master's Degree in Color Processing for employees completing informational assignment, 1965
    - Kodak Photographic Training Department Orientation (notebook), 1952
    - Kodak Color Print and Processing and Photographic Technology Informational Assignment (notebook), 1965
- Periodicals Series, 1907-1985 and undated
  Publications relating to photography and commercial activities related to photography. The majority are published by Kodak. Audiences include amateur and professional photographers, employees, and salespersons. Holdings are not complete in most cases. Arranged alphabetically by periodical title, and therein by volume numbers and dates. When it is not clear how many issues there are of each title by reading the volumes and dates, item numbers are given after the title.
  - Contents of Box: (Box 23)
    - Applied Photography
      For professional photographers. A "source book of examples." Contains short articles on photographs in advertising, many large illustrative photographs featuring various photographers and art directors, and highlights from Kodak Roundtable discussions of photographic issues. First run of each issue features a theme (Composition, Lighting and Interiors, etc.).
      - Old run: 1:2 (July 1931), 2:2 (Apr. 1932), 2:4 (Oct. 1932), No. 9-13 (July 1933-Sept. 1935)
      - New Run: 1-7 (1954-1957), 9-12 (1957-1959), 14 (1960)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 24)
    - Applied Photography, (55 items)
      - 17 (1962), 19-23 (1963-1964), 25 (1965), 28-29 (1966), 34 (1967), 36 (1968), 46 (1970), 49 (1972), 54 (1973), 60-61 (1975-1976)
    - Camera Works Bulletin
      For employees. Contains lists of employee suggestions adopted with monetary reward, articles on safety, information on employee clubs (Glee Clubs etc.), inspirational poems and paragraphs.
      - 2:3 (Nov. 25, 1913), 6:3-6:4 (June-Sept. 1916), 7:1-7:2 (Jan.-Mar. 1917), 7:4 (July 1917)
    - The Cine-Kodak News
      For amateurs and the general public. Some original mailing envelopes. Contains how-to articles (stills, shooting in sunlight, focusing techniques, seasonal film hints, etc.), advice columns, information on new products and Kodak services, and "Good Shots" section featuring amateur photos.
      - 4:5 (Oct. 1927), 5:4 (Sept. 1928), 5:8-6:6 (Jan. 1929-Nov. 1929), 6:9-7:7 (Feb. 1930-Dec. 1930), 7:9-8:5 (Feb. 1931- Nov./Dec. 1931)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 25)
    - The Cine-Kodak News, (80 items)
      - 8:6 ? 8:12 (Jan./Feb. 1932-Jan./Feb. 1933), 9:2 (June/July 1933), 9:5 (Dec. 1933), 10:2-10:6 (Mar./Apr.-Nov./Dec. 1934), 11:1 (Feb. 1935), 11:3-11:5 (May/June-Nov./Dec. 1935), 12:1-13:1 (Feb. 1936-Feb./Mar. 1937), 13:3 (July/Aug. 1937), 14:1-17:2 (Jan./Feb. 1938- Mar./Apr. 1941), 17:4-18:2 (July/Aug. 1941-June 1942)
      - New Run: 19:1-19:2 (June-Fall 1946), Holiday Issue 1946, 20:3 (Fall 1947)
    - Commercial Camera Magazine; subsequent run entitled Commercial Camera: A Supplement to Applied Photography (later called Commercial Camera)
      For professionals (commercial and industrial photographers). Contains many illustrative photographs, information on various types of commercial photography (food illustrations, architectural illustration, etc.), information on new Kodak products, articles on the current trends of photography in advertising (color vs. black-and-white, industry vs. consumer ads, etc.). "Supplement" is thinner, more focused on Kodak products than information by and for colleagues (though some is still present).
      - 8:6-8:12 (Jan./Feb. 1932-Jan./Feb. 1933), 9:2 (June/July 1933), 9:5 (Dec. 1933), 10:2-10:6 (Mar./Apr.-Nov./Dec. 1934), 11:1 (Feb. 1935), 11:3-11:5 (May/June-Nov./Dec. 1935), 12:1-13:1 (Feb. 1936-Feb./Mar. 1937), 13:3 (July/Aug. 1937), 14:1-17:2 (Jan./Feb. 1938-Mar./Apr. 1941), 17:4-18:2 (July/Aug. 1941-June 1942)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 26)
    - Eastman Photographic Bulletin for Salesmen, (30 items)
      For professional salespersons. Contains product information (new, updated, replaced) and suggested uses; tables and charts; pictures of products, and sales hints (e.g. recommending Super Ortho-Press Films for medical photography).
      - 3:1-3:6 (Jan.-June 1939), 3:8-3:9 (Aug.-Sept. 1939), 7:1-7:9 (Jan.-Sept. 1943), 1944:1-4
    - Home Movies and Professional Cine-Photographer; by July, 1959 called Home Movies (non-Kodak serial)
      For amateurs and the general public using 8 mm and 16 mm films. Features many advertisements for photo products; information on world-wide 8mm and 16mm movie clubs; "Cine Capsules" column with short tips on film-making; features on professionals ("Hollywood Pros at work"); articles on angles, make-up use, splicing, caring for your equipment, etc.; and letters from the public.
      - 25:1-26:10 (Jan. 1958-Oct. 1959)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 27)
    - The Kodak Magazine, (53 items)
      For employees. Contains photographs of employees in the armed services during war years; articles on wartime issues (bonds, conditions in England, rationing, etc.); information on employee clubs and events; information on Kodak Company growth, history, and branches around the world; sections devoted to events and people of each factory (Hawk-Eye, Kodak Park, etc.); and tips for employees on safety, home building, health and hygiene, interior decoration, and even vegetable cookery.
      - 1:1-1:3 (June-Aug. 1920), 1:5-3:2 (Oct. 1920-July 1922), 3:4-5:7 (Sept. 1922-Dec. 1924)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 28)
    - The Kodak Magazine, (60 items)
      - 5:8-6:1 (Jan.-June 1925), 6:3 (Aug. 1925), 6:5-6:11 (Oct. 1925-Apr. 1926), 7:1-10:9 (June 1926-Feb. 1930), 10:11-11:1 (Apr.-June 1930)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 29)
    - The Kodak Magazine (circa 1935 became Kodak: A Magazine for Eastman Employees), (47 items)
      - 11:2-11:9 (July 1930-Feb. 1931), 11:11-12:10-11 (Apr. 1931-Mar./Apr. 1932), 13:1-2 (June/July 1932), 13:4 (Sept. 1932), 14:1-2 (June-Aug. 1935), 17:4 (Aug. 1938), 18:1 (Jan. 1939), 18:3 (Mar. 1939), 18:6-18:8 (June-Aug. 1939), 18:10 (Oct. 1939), 19:6-19:8 (June-Aug. 1940), 19:10 (Oct. 1940), 19:12 (Dec. 1940), 20:2-20:3 (Feb.-Mar. 1941), 21:4 (Apr. 1942), 21:9 (Sept. 1942), 21:12-22:6 (Dec. 1942-June 1943), 23:3 (Mar. 1944), 23:5-23:6 (May-June 1944), 23:8 (Aug. 1944)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 30)
    - Kodak Movie News
      For amateurs and the general public taking 8mm and 16mm films. Comes with plastic magazine holder. Contains basics of film-making (pacing, distance, hot weather filming and other seasonal techniques etc.); "Good Shots" pages with amateur film clippings; information on Kodak movie aids, viewers, and other products; ideas for amateur films; letters to the editor; advice columns; and public contests.
      - 2:4-3:5 (July/Aug. 1954-Christmas 1955), 4:1-5:1 (Winter 1956-Winter 1956/7), 6:1-16:3 (Winter 1958-Winter 1968/9)
    - Kodak Park Bulletin
      For employees. Contains lists of employee suggestions implemented and monetary awards given; employee events; patriotic articles on the military and the war; features on specific employees; and humorous cartoons.
      - 20:5 (May 1917), 21:1 (Jan. 1918), 22:2-22:3 (Feb.-Mar. 1919), 22:7 (July 1919), 22:11-23:3-4 (Nov. 1919-Mar./Apr. 1920)
    - The Kodak Salesman
      For professional sales staff. Comes with some original mailing envelopes. Contains humorous comics, poems, and stories conveying sales morals ("A fellow ought to know his game well enough to play it outside of hours"); information about and sneak previews of Kodak ads and promotions (e.g., campus ads, seasonal ads, photo contests, etc.); hints on sales (allow the customer to handle the merchandise, show related items in pairs, etc.) and targeting specific markets (farmers, boy scouts, sportsmen, new parents); and information on new Kodak merchandise.
      - 5:11 (Nov. 1919), 6:3-4 (Mar.-Apr. 1920), 6:6 (June 1920), 8:7 (July 1922), 9:1-11:1 (Jan. 1923-Jan. 1925), 12:12 (Dec. 1926), 14:6 (June 1928)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 31)
    - The Kodak Salesman (by 1930 has tear-sheet in front of "confidential" Kodak Trade Circular every month)
      - 16:1-9 (Jan.-Sept. 1930), 16:11-17:9 (Nov. 1930-Sept. 1931), 17:11-12 (Nov.-Dec. 1931), 19:12 (Dec. 1933), 21:11 (Nov. 1935), 22:2 (Feb. 1936), 23:1-12 (Jan.-Dec. 1937), 24:2-9 (Feb.-Sept. 1938), 24:11-12 (Nov.-Dec. 1938), 29:1 (Jan./Feb. 1943), 32:2 (Mar./Apr. 1946), 34:10-12 (Oct.-Dec. 1948)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 32)
    - Photo Marketing; formerly Photo Developments (non-Kodak serial)
      For professionals (dealers/finishers); official magazine of the Master Photo Dealers' and Finishers' Association. Contains "Sales Scents" idea column; advice from experts and colleagues; many ads for photographic products (as well as section devoted to them called "Scouting the Market"); column on retail advertising; articles on customer service; and information on convention of MPD and FA.
      - 40:2-5 (Feb.-May 1965), 40:7-8 (July-Aug. 1965), 41:2-5 (Feb.-May 1966)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 33)
    - The Professional Photographer (non-Kodak serial)
      For professional photographers; official journal of the Photographers' Association of America Contains many ads for photography products; information on exhibits and conventions; professional advice with such issues as price setting and coping with film shortages; series of analyses of one photograph per issue giving constructive criticism; features on individual photographers.
      - 70:1659-71: 1591 (Feb. 1943-Dec. 1944), 73:1604-1615 (Jan.-Dec. 1946)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 34)
    - Studio Light
      Various titles: until 1908, Aristo Eagle; circa 1909, Studio Light and the Aristo Eagle; circa 1913, Studio Light, incorporating the Aristo Eagle and the Artura Bulletin; by 1931, Studio Light; between 1946 and 1950, called Studio Light Bulletin and/or Studio Light.
      - Aristo Eagle: 7:11 (Dec. 1907), 8:4 (May 1908), 8:10 (Nov. 1908)
      - Studio Light (and the Aristo Eagle): 1:9 (Nov. 1909)
      - Studio Light (incorporating other titles): 4:11 (Jan. 1913), 5:2-4 (Apr.-June 1913)
      - Studio Light: 23:7 (Sept. 1931), 23:9-10 (Nov.-Dec. 1931), 27:2 (June 1936), 27:5 (Dec. 1936), 28:5 (Apr. 1938), 29:1-3 (Oct. 1938-May 1939), 29:5 (Sept. 1939), 29:1-30 (Jan./Feb.-Aug./Sept. 1940), 30:4 (Dec. 1940), 30:5-6 (Mar.-June 1941), 31:1 (June 1942), 32:1 (Aug. 1943)
      - Studio Light Bulletin (and Studio Light): Mar. 1946, May-June 1946, Mar. 1947, July 1947, Sept. 1947, Nov. 1947, Apr. 1948, July 1948, Sept. 1948, Dec. 1948, Mar. 1949, July 1949, Sept. 1949
      - Studio Light: Jan. 1950, Mar. 1950, Aug. 1950, Dec. 1950, Spr. 1951, Fall 1951, Spr. 1952, Fall 1952, Spr.-Summer 1953, Winter 1953, Spr. 1954, Fall 1954-Winter 1954/5, Summer 1955, Winter 1955/6-Spr. 1956, Fall 1956-Winter 1956, Fall 1957, Spr. 1958, Fall 1958
  - Contents of Box: (Box 35)
    - Studio Light
      - 48:2 (1959), 49:1-2 (1960), 50:1-3 (1961), 52:1-3 (1963), 53:2-3 (1964), 54:1-3 (1965), 55:4 (1967), 56:3 (1967), 57:1-3 (1968-1969)
      - New Run: 2-4 (1971-1972), Anniversary Issue (1901-1976), Centennial Issue (1880-1980)
  - Contents of Box: (Box 36)
    - [Untitled] (covers missing, title undetermined)
      For professional photographers. Contains many ads, chiefly for Kodak products. Also offers trade articles (sales methods, hot weather developing, etc.), information on photographic tools (printing papers, innovations in color photography), and information on new Kodak products and sales.
      - 18:4 (Feb./Mar. 1940), 18:6 (July 1940), 19:3-4 (Jan./Feb.-Mar./Apr. 1941), 20:1 (Apr. 1942)
    - Audio-Visual Notes From Kodak
      For professionals. Contains information on Kodak products, and articles on using audio-visual equipment (slide cropping, loading slide trays, storyboarding, presentation design).
      - 1977, 1978
    - Bulletin for the Graphic Arts
      For professional photographers. Features articles on professional topics (halftones, stopping lenses, etc.) linked to highlights of useful Kodak products; illustrative photographs; and features on Kodak services.
      - 7 (1945), 13 (undated)
    - Eastman Organic Chemical Bulletin
      For professionals. Includes article presented at International Quantum Electronics Conference in June 1974 (highly technical information on quantum yields, etc.), and a list of laser dyes available from Kodak (several of which are mentioned in the article).
      - 46:3 (1974)
    - Kodak
      Seems to be for employees. Contains information on policies relating to Kodak employees in the military, new Kodak military teaching films, excerpts from speeches by Lincoln.
      - 21:2 (Feb. 1942)- excerpt
    - Kodak Bulletin for the Graphic Arts
      For professional photographers. Contains articles based on technical memoranda or convention papers, on professional topics (halftones, duotones, posterized negatives, mechanized film processing, etc.). Also offers information on Kodak products and articles on their use, with many illustrative photographs.
      - 2-6 (undated), 8-9 (undated), 13 (1968), 15 (1968), 17 (1969), 19 (undated)
    - Kodak Camera Club News
      For amateurs and the general public. Contains picture-taking tips (taking photographic membership cards, creative still-lifes or reflections, etc.), information on new Kodak books and products, and information on specific camera clubs (e.g., Toronto Camera Club). Issues lack volume numbers and other issue identifiers.